<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>TS1</title>
 <link href="https://burnedsap.github.io/ts1https://burnedsap.github.io/ts1/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="https://burnedsap.github.io/ts1https://burnedsap.github.io/ts1/"/>
 <updated>2021-09-07T20:48:58-04:00</updated>
 <id>https://burnedsap.github.io/ts1</id>
 <author>
   <name>Salil Parekh</name>
   <email>pares667@newschool.edu</email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>Reflection</title>
   <link href="https://burnedsap.github.io/ts1https://burnedsap.github.io/ts1/2021/05/11/reflection/"/>
   <updated>2021-05-11T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>https://burnedsap.github.io/ts1/2021/05/11/reflection</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;reflection&quot;&gt;Reflection&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hello, I’m Salil. I studied exhibition design, but since then I’ve wandered off into technology, social impact, and digital spaces. I’m still wandering around, but hoping to find what I want to do soon. I used to work at a wonderful studio called Quicksand, in Delhi and Goa. In the few years I spent there, I worked on a wide range of projects, from digital heritage, human centered design, social impact, entrepreneurship, sexual and reproductive health, digital art, and even producing large scale festivals! At one point I realised that I did like working with new technology, but understood that I had a limited understanding of what it really means to work with any kind of technology. It was easy to be enamored with the exciting possibilities, but not so much when thinking about what it really meant to use it. After speaking with a few friends and peers, I stumbled upon the MFA DT programme and somehow got admission. I’m sure it’s an administrative error, but we’ll gloss over that. I remember speaking with Richard The during the interview for the admission, and telling him why I’d like to study at The New School. I described a feeling of wanting to learn more about how to use technology for social good, especially in the Indian context. A few years ago, I worked on a project which was looked at delivering instructions to the users of an abortion pill, in rural Bihar. After months of user research, we realised that the best solution was to use an IVR and SMS based system. I enjoyed working on this project, given the context and the challenges that came with it. I also realised that I had perhaps stopped learning, or that my learning mindset was not as developed as it should have been. I needed to learn how to learn again. Perhaps a small &lt;a href=&quot;https://burnedsap.github.io/bitmap-game/&quot;&gt;game&lt;/a&gt; describes me best. 
Post MortemThe first year of the MFA DT programme has been fairly hectic. I’ve explored a wide variety of topics and mediums, with some projects more noteworthy than others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Learning the basics of code alongside more complicated questions around computers in Critical Computation was a lot of fun, and I got to understand the ‘digital fabric’ of the web as I’d like to say. The fast paced project sprints forced me to get creative within the constraints of time, and learn new skills. Some of the skills learnt in this class later came in handy when creating the Calendar of Conflict for the Design for This Century class. The &lt;a href=&quot;http://calendar-of-conflict.glitch.me/&quot;&gt;Calendar of Conflict&lt;/a&gt; is a data driven outlook on the news in India. Although flawed in many aspects, the visualisation shows just how often conflict is mentioned in print news, as opposed to the fictional picture of India painted by state-sponsored TV media. The methodology isn’t perfect, but it does give a broader perspective on the news we read everyday. The project was subsequently showcased at NYC Open Data Week, which validated the value in seeing news from a different perspective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My fascination with TV news media in India appeared in a class which explored the politics of aesthetics, wherein I explored how sharing of &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/document/d/1FDIBA4j-cWu4KBDKUd1gVIa-En5phKQYMEsw2Kh_FAg/edit?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;doctored screenshots&lt;/a&gt; of TV news media could be used to subvert the narrative (or rather, propaganda). This is of course, highly unethical, and although I never did end up sharing the doctored screenshots on social media, it did expose a petulant side of myself that I didn’t acknowledge before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major Studio 1 encouraged me to embrace this petulancy–so much so that my final presentation was titled, ‘&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1TTwmrKbkko9Uuqr_YuX6hkPqIJZD7Gd6-vJWotu_AeA/edit?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;Journey of Petulancy&lt;/a&gt;’. I realised that it was to get upset about something–and use that energy to drive my work forward. MS1 is also where I started to drift toward the speculative realm, a theme which continued well into the second semester. MS1 started off with the intent to reclaim the power of technology from the powerful few who define it. This initially manifested itself in the form of a few small projects, such as the &lt;a href=&quot;https://ms1-salil.glitch.me/posts/museum-of-stolen-artifacts.html&quot;&gt;Museum of Stolen Artifacts&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://ms1-salil.glitch.me/posts/digital-dioramas.html&quot;&gt;Digital Dioramas&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://ms1-salil.glitch.me/posts/down-the-rabbit-hole.html&quot;&gt;Down the Rabbit Hole&lt;/a&gt;. Each of these projects looked at how technology could be used to subvert a narrative. Thereafter, my focus narrowed down to questioning the concept of ‘healthy technology’, and specifically looking at what this term means for different users. I created speculative products which would fit the description of ‘healthy technology’ for 3 different users. What does healthy technology look like for an introvert who doesn’t feel in control of their digital life? What does it look like for an RWA Committee Head looking to become self reliant in monitoring their community. Perhaps the most exciting of all, what does it look like for a social media troll in search of technology that helps them do what they do best. It was interesting to work on designing objects which were in a way, an oxymoron. Healthy technology for social media trolls? In retrospect, it brings to light the decisions one would make when keeping the user’s best interests in mind, which in this case would be social media trolls. Here’s a &lt;a href=&quot;https://ms1-salil.glitch.me/posts/ideas-in-form-part-3.html&quot;&gt;breakdown&lt;/a&gt; of the objects I ended up creating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the second semester, I decided to take as many classes as I possibly could. Like the previous semester, I wanted to bring in some of the synergy between courses to augment my thinking and process. A class on Dark Data helped me get a better understanding of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1BSjCQUDRUlM9q2bYv94X-WqQJQVpQBaJR_jR0z7Xqi4/edit?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;nitty gritties of the GDPR&lt;/a&gt;, which then came in handy when in &lt;a href=&quot;https://mfadt.parsons.edu/darkdata/2021/I-Have-Nothing-to-Hide&quot;&gt;my contribution&lt;/a&gt; to the Dark Data zine, which was about India’s soon to be operational National Social Registry. Wading through the legalese of court documents, policies, and bills helped me better understand the murky depths of how our data can be used for a wide range of purposes. It also helped improve my legal vocabulary and read between the lines, which is always a useful skill to have. Apart from Major Studio 2, I took the Designed Realities Simulated Life classes, and serendipitously, these three classes had plenty of overlaps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Designed Realities, taken by Fiona Raby and Anthony Dunne, was great class, and helped me hone my speculative design skills. My prompt for the semester was, “What does water think?” A simple question, but there’s lots to think about. This was a class I looked forward to every week, simply because I felt like I had to get outside of my comfort zone. I had to work hard week in, week out, to have something I could present in class, especially to an audience of other students who were excessively talented. I’m quite competitive, and nothing drives me forward more than being in a group of people who are far better than me in every way. It is incredibly satisfying to walk away at the end of the semester with a large quantity of work which I’m mostly happy with. The project culminated in the creation of a &lt;a href=&quot;https://drive.google.com/drive/folders/1-W-xyQMOPM7p4G72-Nc272r5CQl3zgoN?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;publication&lt;/a&gt; which describes a world in which water is given far more importance. The publications only show 10% of the work from the class. The other 90% of the work was ultimately rejected, but was critical in helping me create that 10%. To quote Edison, “I have not failed. I’ve just found 10,000 ways that won’t work.” This motto rang true, not only for my work in Designed Realities, but also for Major Studio 2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major Studio 2 started off with a simple question: What does local, contextual, and sustainable machine intelligence look like? This led me to research TinyML, and various instances of machine learning being used for social good, or to empower communities who previously did not have access to such technology. Beyond that, I couldn’t find many more precedents, so naturally I looked to the future–a future in which local, contextual, and sustainable machine intelligence is a reality. Through a &lt;a href=&quot;https://burnedsap.github.io/ms2/&quot;&gt;5-in-5 sprint&lt;/a&gt;, I visualised this future through various forms; a timeline, objects, a manifesto, questioning the intelligence of rocks, and creating a basic form of intelligence. Through the process of making, I started questioning the very definition of intelligence, and what we, as humans consider intelligent beings to be. I wanted to view the world through a different lens, a non-human one, and so my research question changed to: “What does a planet-centred machine intelligence look like?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I did my research, and worked on unraveling this question, created speculative artefacts to help me work through this process. The first of which was a patent application (what else?) for a &lt;a href=&quot;https://burnedsap.github.io/ms2/2021/03/29/protoype-1/&quot;&gt;World Wide Flora Network Intelligence System&lt;/a&gt; (WWFNIS). The patent outlines some of the possibilities of an intelligence system which wasn’t a human centered one. The WWFNIS uses a NeuralLink (a speculative device) which taps into the root networks of plants and trees in order to communicate with them. What would an internet of trees look like? Would the increase in communication between floral entities around the world lead to faster evolution? Would it lead to a decrease in diseases and viruses if information is shared at a far greater rate?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of trying to answer the initial research question, this project would be far more effective if it asks more questions. Could I, through this project, get the viewer to wonder what the world would look like through a non-human lens? Can I get them to think of the possibilities if this scenario were to become reality?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Parallely, I was actively developing an Artificial Life system in the Simulated Life class. What better way to understand intelligence than to actually create one? An Artificial Life system (ALife system) is an artificial ecosystem which attempts to replicate a natural ecosystem (along with its complexities), with multiple entities which interact with each other. I wanted to create an ALife system which used alternate metrics of survival. I wanted to see if there’s any difference between a species’s chances of survival if it chose to share resources, or respected the environment. It was a complicated undertaking, and took a fairly long time to set up a system which achieved homeostasis. The &lt;a href=&quot;http://burnedsap.github.io/pond/&quot;&gt;process of creating the ALife system&lt;/a&gt; was fascinating as I grappled with the intricacies of decision making for the agents I was creating. How do the agents decide what to do? For example, if they’re low on food, but see a predator nearby, do they take a chance on grabbing the food, or simply run away? If an agent waits to eat plants till they’re mature and have replicated other plants, does it help create a sustainable food source which could potentially help the entire species survive for longer? Which characteristics are more desirable in an agent? Does that change when the context changes? Intelligence, as it’s very essence, is to make a decision. Exploring the idea of non-human intelligence from a top and bottom perspective was certainly very interesting. It may not have contributed much to work in MS2, but I definitely learnt a lot from the process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the biggest challenges with any sort of speculative design work is the communication aspect of it. This is something that I grappled with during the last sprint of the Designing Realities class, as well as MS2. I had all these ideas, concepts, and artefacts, but no clear way to present them unless I was present making sense of it. None of what I had created was capable of making sense by itself. This is of course nothing new. A quick glance at most speculative design work will reaffirm this. A lot of it doesn’t make sense, and some of it is just plain ridiculous. I didn’t figure out a solution to this for either class, but I did take an attempt at trying to create something which wouldn’t require me to provide context.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Designed Realities, I compiled my work within a familiar format–spreads of a home interior and furnishings magazine. Although the content of the spreads is from an alternate reality, the format creates a familiar environment which makes it slightly easier to understand the content. I tried a variety of other formats–notebooks of an inventor, resplendent with scribbles, drawings and the rantings of a lunatic; a shop window full of strange objects; visual poetry–yet none seemed to work as well as ‘House to Home’, the fictional magazine I created to showcase how objects which work water fit in a home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For MS2, I ended up creating a version of myself, which would explain my thoughts. I embodied my project within a conversation with myself. Titled &lt;a href=&quot;https://burnedsap.github.io/ms2/Daydreaming_mk2.html&quot;&gt;Daydreaming&lt;/a&gt;, it’s an interactive text piece which takes the viewer through my thought process and introduces various speculative artefacts. So far the feedback has been fairly positive, which is reassuring, but I still feel that the format for speculative work has yet to be figured out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s been a few things which have stood out to me over the course of two semesters. This is a very shallow snapshot, given that I haven’t had any time whatsoever to reflect (the bizarre timing of the submission of this piece is to blame–I honestly don’t see much value in my writing at this point. The semester concluded mere hours ago.) here, so please keep this in mind. One, is that it’s okay to be angry, it’s okay to take energy from being upset with something. I honestly do not know what I want to do after this, and perhaps there’s a clue in what drives me to work and produce what I do. Second, is that there’s value in seeing things from a different perspective, preferable from a perspective that you don’t often think about. Third, I need to have more confidence in how I view the world. There is value in how I see things, no matter how strange or crass it might be. I need to have more confidence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m here to challenge myself, and so I need to push myself everyday, no matter what. I haven’t been doing enough of that, and it shows in the quality of my work in the second semester.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Accepting that I don’t have answers to everything, and that sometimes, the only correct answer is –’I don’t know.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do wish to learn more, and I intend to keep learning, keep making, keep doing whatever I can to understand more of what I don’t know. I’m taking a class on economics this summer. I would like to have taken more classes, but credit limits have severely handicapped my ambitions. Nevertheless, there’s enough to learn from. I will also be applying for projects/grants/proposals through the summer, and will be working on an air-pollution related project for which I’ve received funding from Khoj for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for what I’d like to work on for next semester? I don’t know. But from the projects I’ve worked on this semester, I see speculative design being an integral part of my practice. I’m also interested in the future of computing and non-human intelligence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m still yet to process everything that has happened so far, and the submission of this writing is fairly untimely, given that I haven’t had more than a few hours of reflecting on the semester. I’m sure there will be more that will occur to me, but I’m certain that the writing in this state is incomplete and will need more time and energy to get something which is actually meaningful, and not just a shallow look back at the academic year. I hope to update this piece–not necessarily for you, the intended reader, but rather for myself. I’ve only recently found value in reflecting on my work, and I hope to continue doing so.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Final Project</title>
   <link href="https://burnedsap.github.io/ts1https://burnedsap.github.io/ts1/2021/05/02/final-project/"/>
   <updated>2021-05-02T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>https://burnedsap.github.io/ts1/2021/05/02/final-project</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-project&quot;&gt;Final Project&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I continued working on the final prototype, and have added visuals to the story, as well as cleaning it up and adding more content. I feel that this is an interesting experiment, especially with the intent of having this exist without having me provide context and explain it–a challenge for any speculative design project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, see my &lt;a href=&quot;https://burnedsap.github.io/ms2/Daydreaming_mk2.html&quot;&gt;daydreams&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Final Paper</title>
   <link href="https://burnedsap.github.io/ts1https://burnedsap.github.io/ts1/2021/04/25/final-paper/"/>
   <updated>2021-04-25T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>https://burnedsap.github.io/ts1/2021/04/25/final-paper</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-paper&quot;&gt;Final Paper&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read the paper &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/document/d/1b531h3itJrg-LSDdfhLr3kCUkg4qiTNSBKtDH8lUfDw/edit?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s always work to be done, and everyday I see new ideas I can add to the paper. It’s as ready as it can be today. Really appreciate everyone’s feedback!&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Paper Draft</title>
   <link href="https://burnedsap.github.io/ts1https://burnedsap.github.io/ts1/2021/04/15/paper-draft/"/>
   <updated>2021-04-15T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>https://burnedsap.github.io/ts1/2021/04/15/paper-draft</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;paper-draft&quot;&gt;Paper Draft&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the paper draft &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/document/d/1S3uNmKHWyzc11DVf6lGI_poF7qFNSihdUzqs0E8oUOo/edit?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still needs more work, but it’s slowly taking shape.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Prototype 3</title>
   <link href="https://burnedsap.github.io/ts1https://burnedsap.github.io/ts1/2021/04/12/prototype-3/"/>
   <updated>2021-04-12T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>https://burnedsap.github.io/ts1/2021/04/12/prototype-3</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;prototype-3&quot;&gt;Prototype 3&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third prototype is a lucid journey into the thinking behind the ideas I’m proposing. The best way to do so? &lt;a href=&quot;https://burnedsap.github.io/ms2/Daydreaming.html&quot;&gt;Daydream&lt;/a&gt; with me while I speak to myself.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Prototype 2</title>
   <link href="https://burnedsap.github.io/ts1https://burnedsap.github.io/ts1/2021/04/06/prototype-2/"/>
   <updated>2021-04-06T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>https://burnedsap.github.io/ts1/2021/04/06/prototype-2</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;prototype-2&quot;&gt;Prototype 2&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inspired by the zine Computer Lib/Dream Machines created by Ted Nelson, I’ve created a &lt;a href=&quot;https://burnedsap.github.io/ms2/media/Alternate%20Visions%20of%20Machines%20and%20Machine%20Intelligence.pdf&quot;&gt;zine of my own&lt;/a&gt;, with seeds of ideas sketching out different possibilities in which a future with alternative visions of machine intelligence could look like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Feedback welcome as always!&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Paper Outline</title>
   <link href="https://burnedsap.github.io/ts1https://burnedsap.github.io/ts1/2021/04/04/paper-outline/"/>
   <updated>2021-04-04T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>https://burnedsap.github.io/ts1/2021/04/04/paper-outline</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;paper-outline&quot;&gt;Paper Outline&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the paper outline &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/document/d/1wrc3YqoqVWbt49HtiFPR5yoI6iy-nw8geHSU5BNQntU/edit?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m definitely still confused about what I’m trying to do, and what my project is about. As I write the paper and create the prototypes, the fog lifts and I’m able to see with more clarity. The next prototype is certainly going to be interesting, if not fun!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Prototype 1</title>
   <link href="https://burnedsap.github.io/ts1https://burnedsap.github.io/ts1/2021/03/29/protoype-1/"/>
   <updated>2021-03-29T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>https://burnedsap.github.io/ts1/2021/03/29/protoype-1</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;prototype-1&quot;&gt;Prototype 1&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the mid-term presentations and reviewing the feedback I received, I found myself cornered by my own work. I enjoyed the journey so far, as outlined in the mid-term presentation, but I find myself feeling quite lost now. The question I highlighted at the end of my presentation: “What does a planet-centered machine intelligence look like?” now seems insurmountable. From the feedback I received, the one that stood out to me the most was, “Instigate questions”. I started on this journey asking myself questions, and the way forward was perhaps in the same direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A medium that I find particularly interesting is that of patent applications. They’re often used as pointers to get an understanding of new technologies under development, and elicit strong responses if they’re noteworthy. Exactly what I’d like to create. Hence, I set about creating a patent application which paints a vision of an alternate world where planet-centered machine intelligence exists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;View the patent application &lt;a href=&quot;https://burnedsap.github.io/ms2/media/WWFNIS%20Draft%20Patent%20Application.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Feedback of any sort is welcome!&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Midterm Presentation</title>
   <link href="https://burnedsap.github.io/ts1https://burnedsap.github.io/ts1/2021/03/08/midterm-pres/"/>
   <updated>2021-03-08T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>https://burnedsap.github.io/ts1/2021/03/08/midterm-pres</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;midterm-presentation&quot;&gt;Midterm Presentation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;View the midterm presentation &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/burnedsap/ms2/raw/main/media/MS2%20Midterm%20Deck%20Salil.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>5 in 5 (5)</title>
   <link href="https://burnedsap.github.io/ts1https://burnedsap.github.io/ts1/2021/02/28/5in5-5/"/>
   <updated>2021-02-28T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>https://burnedsap.github.io/ts1/2021/02/28/5in5-5</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;5-in-5--5&quot;&gt;5 in 5 – 5&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;making-a-thing&quot;&gt;Making a thing&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enough talk, time to get started on actually making an intelligence. It’s genuinely mind-blowing to read about other kinds of intelligences, and a talk at the World Science Festival took it a step further. I sincerely urge you to listen to this panel speak. In the midst of some heavy science flavoured flirting, you’ll realise how we’re living in the midst of some truly alien creatures right here on our very own planet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;450&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/RpwW9Lw2Ku4&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After all this listening, I simply had to take a crack at trying to create my own intelligent being. I started coding using p5js and after some thinking, I decided to take an interative approach at creating this intelligence. First, I created the Being. A simple white square on the screen. It’s very existence on the screen hinted at intelligence. I could’ve simply left it at this stage, content with the intelligence it had.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/ms2/media/ezgif.com-video-to-gif-8.gif&quot; alt=&quot;ezgif.com-video-to-gif-8&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I decided to press on further. Eager to give it some capabilities, I blessed it with the ability to move. It would hobble about at random, with no intent or direction. It now existed and could move around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I then gave it a sense, the sense to feel when another presence is close to it. In this case, it can sense the cursor close it’s physical being.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/ms2/media/ezgif.com-video-to-gif-9.gif&quot; alt=&quot;ezgif.com-video-to-gif-9&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To give it a sense of purpose and a way to sustain itself, I then gave it the ability to eat, and additionally the ability to sense food.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/ms2/media/ezgif.com-video-to-gif-10.gif&quot; alt=&quot;ezgif.com-video-to-gif-10&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interact with the intelligent Being here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;600px&quot; height=&quot;600px&quot; src=&quot;https://editor.p5js.org/burnedsap/embed/FI7D-q5KP&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although it was challenging coding these rules in, the process of doing so did get me thinking about intelligence, and the purpose of my creation. Staring at a blank screen, I couldn’t think of anything radical, and so I give it an intelligence I was familiar with-locomotion, eating, and sensing. My context heavily influenced the decisions I made. Given enough time and space, perhaps I might be able to break out of this context bubble and think of different kinds of intelligences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The value of the intelligence is heavily dependent within the context within which it exists. An ant’s intelligence may not be very useful as a single entity as compared to a nest of ants. Human intelligence may be very well suited for Earth, but could be completely useless on Venus, or on a different plane of existence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Could there be other kinds of intelligences which machine intelligences could adopt? Perhaps intelligences that aren’t purely functional, but serve to add other kinds of value? What would a non-human centered machine intelligence look like? Or a planet-centered one? Time to join the Machinists.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>5 in 5 (4)</title>
   <link href="https://burnedsap.github.io/ts1https://burnedsap.github.io/ts1/2021/02/27/5in5-4/"/>
   <updated>2021-02-27T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>https://burnedsap.github.io/ts1/2021/02/27/5in5-4</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;5-in-5--4&quot;&gt;5 in 5 – 4&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-intelligence-of-rocks&quot;&gt;The Intelligence of Rocks&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The phrase ‘dumb as a rock’ is quite an interesting phrase. It means being terminally stupid, unintelligent, and perhaps it might just have started off as referring to someone who is unable to speak. In the context of exploring machine intelligence, it’s only apt that all kinds of intelligence be studied. Intelligence is defined as ‘the ability to acquire and apply knowledge and skills’, and it’s fair to say that a rock certainly does not fulfill this definition, at least not in the paradigm we believe in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If for a moment, you step away from our current human-centered understanding of intelligence, you might just see the world in a new light. Of course, we do acknowledge the intelligence of entities such as animals, trees, and micro-organisms, but we do so from a human intelligence perspective. Squirrels are strategic because they create pretend to hide nuts in fake holes to fool rivals. Sheep are social animals as they move in flocks. These are aspects of intelligence we understand and relate to. But what about the parts on the intelligence spectrum that we don’t understand? A rock, or any other unintelligeble entity could fall on that scale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What if a rock operates on a plane we simple cannot see? They’ve been around since the beginning of time, and have seen the best and the worst of this planet, and other planets in the universe. There are many different types of rocks, formed through different processes-does that mean they have different intelligences? Is a sedimentary rock more intelligent than a grain of sand? Or do they have different kinds of intelligences? Perhaps a rock formed over millions of years, with layers of lava cooling over different periods of time gives it a different kind of intelligence, one connected with experience and age. Rocks are often composed of elements that are completely different from the ones that form our makeup. Rather interestingly, rocks contain silicon, an element that is the backbone of our computing, and by extension, the building blocks of machine intelligence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the intelligence of a rock is the reason for it’s existence. If natural selection is anything to go by, rocks have existed far before us, and will continue to exist until the heat death of the universe. The intent of this line of thought isn’t to prove that rocks are intelligent entities, but to draw attention to other non-human kinds of intelligence. Parameters and metrics which we don’t usually tend to think of as intellligent doesn’t necessarily mean that it does not have any intelligence at all. Perhaps being as ‘dumb as a rock’ is actually good thing, we may never truly be as intelligent as a rock.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>5 in 5 (3)</title>
   <link href="https://burnedsap.github.io/ts1https://burnedsap.github.io/ts1/2021/02/26/5in5-3/"/>
   <updated>2021-02-26T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>https://burnedsap.github.io/ts1/2021/02/26/5in5-3</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;5-in-5--3&quot;&gt;5 in 5 – 3&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New ideals and paradigms of computing are exciting times to be in, and there’s no better way to indulge than to think of the radical ways in which computing and machine intelligence can be re-designed. The first prototypes of the CCC (Closed Cycle Computing) standard are an exciting breed of machines which promise (finally) a sustainable way to compute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;clickertrainer&quot;&gt;ClickerTrainer&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ClickerTrainer is an analogue take on training intelligences. The handheld device contains no batteries, and solely uses a clicker to momentarily power a capacitor. The capacitor provides a burst of energy which is used to power the computer and register data. The dial on the device adjusts the moment of power generated by the button using pre-set tensioners. It is also used to input different values for the training.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/ms2/media/IObj-10001_0001-e.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;IObj-10001_0001-e&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/ms2/media/IObj-10003_0003.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;IObj-10003_0003&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;hand-cranked-plantpc&quot;&gt;Hand Cranked PlantPC&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This hand cranked beauty is the computing centerpiece of your home. With a houseplant providing the natural intelligence and training data, all it takes to power it is a few turns of the crank to keep the process of osmosis and photosynthesis going for a while. The modular design allows for the addition of compute models and plants to build your collection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/ms2/media/IObj-10009_0009-e.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;IObj-10009_0009-e&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/ms2/media/IObj-10004_0004.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;IObj-10004_0004&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;psoup-plank&quot;&gt;PSoup Plank&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Designed for hobbyists, this module solely uses natural intelligence as it’s compute element. The closed loop cycle is enclosed in a crystal with 3 input/output channels to interact with it. Analogue dials provide easy to access to the controls in a server stack setup. Multiply the compute power with multiple planks connected via a sterilised plumbing system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/ms2/media/IObj-10010_0010-e.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;IObj-10010_0010-e&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/ms2/media/IObj-10013_0013.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;IObj-10013_0013&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>5 in 5 (2)</title>
   <link href="https://burnedsap.github.io/ts1https://burnedsap.github.io/ts1/2021/02/25/5in5-2/"/>
   <updated>2021-02-25T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>https://burnedsap.github.io/ts1/2021/02/25/5in5-2</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;5-in-5--2&quot;&gt;5 in 5 – 2&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wanted to explore one of the events from the timeline in greater detail. I felt the Machinists were an interesting group to find out more about. The Machinists formed as a response to the changing landscape of technology and the rise of Closed Cycle Computing (CCC). A group with extreme views, they released a manifesto just after the announcement of the CCC standard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is the manifesto:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;machinist-manifesto&quot;&gt;Machinist Manifesto&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the beginnings of time, humans have used their creations to establish their species on the top of the food chain. Their creations have dominated every other creature in existence, and effectively helped humans colonise their own planet. Make no mistake, we were destined to shape planets in our own image. Nature put us on this path as it has intended to. Spaceship Earth needs us to advance and protect it from existential threats. The implosion of our solar system is not the final act in the story of this planet. We were put on this path of dominance to become a multi-planet, multi-system, and eventually, a multi-planar species. We were designed to save our planet from it’s death. The end goal is to live beyond the heat death of the universe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For far too long, we have been looking at our reflection, consumed by our need to save the ecosystem, and atone for our progress as a species. This vain crusade has wasted hundreds of years of potential progress. This setback could very well be the difference that decides the fate of Earth. We must achieve the goal we were created and nurtured for. Our journey started with the first stone we picked up and used to our advantage. This path will take us far beyond the boundaries of our physical reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We salute our brethren in the CCC. Their new models of computation will help destroy the hegemony of the industry. Make no mistake, the destruction of the incumbents is inevitable. The computer is an archaic machine created to serve our needs. Developments in intelligence and machine learning have shown us the path we could have been on. The Earth created us to serve its purpose. We have created machines to serve ours. The machines will create their own entities, which will far surpass us. Our goal is to continue development of these machines, and eventually the creation of machine intelligence, which will augment our capabilities and allow us to make the next leap of our evolution. The power vacuum left in the wake of the sinking vessel of economic greed and political thirst will create a churn. You’re not alone if you too can sense the oncoming chaos. The CCC has ushered in a new reality of multiple intelligences. There is power in diversity, and this diversity will be the driving force of our journey toward the next step.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The development and creation of independent, self sufficient intelligent entities will make for a thriving ecosystem. Natural selection, under our guidance, will select the most efficient path toward the next step of our evolution. No single organisation or corporation can have influence over this process. The process takes precedence over all else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Machinist believes in the following principles:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Our purpose is to ensure the survival of Spaceship Earth, beyond the heat death of the universe&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Respect the process of natural selection, and strive of efficient evolution paths&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Creation of machines to fulfil our goals&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Survivability of Earth is prioritised ahead of the fate of humanity&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The finding of, or the creation of intelligence to succeed humanity to continue the mission of ensuring Earth’s survivability.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>5 in 5 (1)</title>
   <link href="https://burnedsap.github.io/ts1https://burnedsap.github.io/ts1/2021/02/24/5in5-1/"/>
   <updated>2021-02-24T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>https://burnedsap.github.io/ts1/2021/02/24/5in5-1</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;5-in-5--1&quot;&gt;5 in 5 – 1&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To get a better understand of what the future with local machine learning devices will look like, I created a timeline visualising the future. Although purely speculative, the intent is to explore both positive and negative events for a balanced view of the future. The timeline uses time along the x-axis, and degree of preferability along the y-axis. Preferability is quite subjective, and so this is a vision of the future tinted with my thoughts and opinions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/ms2/media/Speculative Timeline.png&quot; alt=&quot;Speculative Timeline&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The yellow marked post-its are the ones I feel are interesting, and do see how the events play out through the timeline!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;View a higher definition PDF file &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/burnedsap/ms2/raw/main/media/Speculative%20Timeline.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Notes from the Future</title>
   <link href="https://burnedsap.github.io/ts1https://burnedsap.github.io/ts1/2021/02/15/futuring-sketches/"/>
   <updated>2021-02-15T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>https://burnedsap.github.io/ts1/2021/02/15/futuring-sketches</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A brief exploration of the future to visualise the impacts of Small ML entities which are contextual and local. Small ML are tiny machine learning models which are trained locally, and are usually low-powered for use in a variety of environments. Although lacking the sheer power of data-centers, they more than make up for it with direct access to live data, and highly contextual learning environments. Under the watchful guidance of a human, their training is far richer and more nuanced which makes for excellent hyperlocal intelligence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;width: 100%;&quot; class=&quot;embed-thumb&quot;&gt; &lt;h1 style=&quot;position: relative;vertical-align: middle;display: inline-block; font-size: 24px; line-height:22px; color: #393939;margin-bottom: 10px; font-weight: 300;font-family: Proxima Nova, sans-serif;&quot;&gt; &lt;img src=&quot;https://app.mural.co/avatar/u622b970f45f2cc69b6ca1290&quot; style=&quot;position: absolute; border-radius: 50%; width: 36px;height: 36px;margin-right: 14px; display: inline-block; margin-top: -6px;margin-right: 10px; vertical-align: middle;&quot; /&gt; &lt;div style=&quot;padding-left:50px&quot;&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;max-width:555px;display: inline-block;overflow: hidden; white-space: nowrap;text-overflow: ellipsis;line-height: 1; height: 25px; margin-top: -3px;&quot;&gt;Futuring Notes&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;position:relative;top:-3px;font-size: 16px; margin-top: -6px; line-height: 24px;color: #393939; font-weight: 300;&quot;&gt; by Salil Parekh&lt;/span&gt; &lt;/div&gt; &lt;/h1&gt; &lt;div style=&quot;position: relative; height: 0;overflow: hidden; height: 400px; max-width: 100%; min-width: 320px; border-width: 1px; border-style: solid; border-color: #d8d8d8;&quot;&gt; &lt;div style=&quot;position: absolute;top: 0;left: 0;z-index: 10; width: 600px; height: 100%;background: url(https://murally.blob.core.windows.net/thumbnails/newschool14/murals/newschool14.1613428072560-602af56890002be3d8de6aec-99a40589-d0d5-4d6b-9a8a-57f1f0cc5b6c.png?v=739a993c-b7a3-421b-b086-0c4073188735) no-repeat center center; background-size: cover;&quot;&gt; &lt;div style=&quot;position: absolute;top: 0;left: 0;z-index: 20;width: 100%; height: 100%;background-color: white;-webkit-filter: opacity(.4);&quot;&gt; &lt;/div&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://app.mural.co/t/newschool14/m/newschool14/1613428072560/e728591c2ba8c44b7be6d0e2a17784efc815ef06&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; style=&quot;transform: translate(-50%, -50%);top: 50%;left: 50%; position: absolute; z-index: 30; border: none; display: block; height: 50px; background: transparent;&quot;&gt; &lt;img src=&quot;https://app.mural.co/static/images/btn-enter-mural.svg&quot; alt=&quot;ENTER THE MURAL&quot; width=&quot;233&quot; height=&quot;50&quot; /&gt; &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/div&gt; &lt;/div&gt; &lt;p style=&quot;margin-top: 10px;margin-bottom: 60px;line-height: 24px; font-size: 16px;font-family: Proxima Nova, sans-serif;font-weight: 400; color: #888888;&quot;&gt; You will be able to edit this mural. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Annotated Bibliography</title>
   <link href="https://burnedsap.github.io/ts1https://burnedsap.github.io/ts1/2021/02/09/annotated-biliography/"/>
   <updated>2021-02-09T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>https://burnedsap.github.io/ts1/2021/02/09/annotated-biliography</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Author Name&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Title&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Citation&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Keywords&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Summary&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Relevance&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Doore, Karen&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1145/2493394.2493418&quot;&gt;Alternate Realities for Computational Thinking&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://dl.acm.org/doi/proceedings/10.1145/2493394&quot;&gt;ICER ‘13: Proceedings of the ninth annual international ACM conference on International computing education research&lt;/a&gt;. August 2013 Pages 171–172&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Social and professional topics, Computing education, Computing educational programs,&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;This paper looks at how Alternate Reality Games (ARGs) can be used “as an educational platform to engage students in a collaborative exploration of the field of computing as a means to increase interest in computing”. This is an interesting approach toward education as it explores new mediums and types of content delivery.&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;A look at new approaches toward education on computers using computers&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Anand, Abhinav, Veljko Pejovic, Elizabeth M. Belding, and David L. Johnson&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1145/2160673.2160698&quot;&gt;VillageCell&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;Proceedings of the Fifth International Conference on Information and Communication Technologies and Development - ICTD ‘12&lt;/em&gt;, March 2012&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Networks, Network architecture, Cross-computing tools and techniques&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;VillageCell uses existing technology stack to create systems which help boost connectivity in areas often left behind by the government and development organisations. This “relies on software defined radios and open-source solutions to provide free local and cheap long-distance communication for remote regions”.&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;The focus on using existing tech stacks is of particular interest to me. The implementation of this does raise some questions which I’d like to keep in mind.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Matthee, K. W., G. Mweemba, A. V. Pais, G. van Stam, and M. Rijken&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1109/ictd.2007.4937391&quot;&gt;Bringing Internet Connectivity to Rural Zambia Using a Collaborative Approach&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;2007 International Conference on Information and Communication Technologies and Development&lt;/em&gt;, 2007&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Web and internet services,  Satellites,  IP networks,  Wireless LAN,  Employment,  Costs,  Bandwidth,  International collaboration,  Africa,  Technological innovation&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Similar to VillageCell, this paper shows how using older tech stacks can be used to provide services. It “operates using satellite terminals (for connection to the Internet) and a wireless local area network.” Especially with regard to the potential use cases of this application.&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Great use of older tech, especially with the uses cases mentioned of helping communities&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Warschauer, Mark&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Technology and Social Inclusion: Rethinking the Digital Divide&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Cambridge, MA: MIT, 2004&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Digital divide, social inclusion&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;A great read which goes into details of “Drawing on theory from political science, economics, sociology, psychology, communications, education, and linguistics, the book examines the ways in which differing access to technology contributes to social and economic stratification or inclusion” with case studies from disaffected countries like the US and developing nations of Brazil, India, China.&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Interesting read-nice direction to head in, if obvious&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Bederson, Benjamin B., James D. Hollan, Ken Perlin, Jonathan Meyer, David Bacon, and George Furnas&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1006/jvlc.1996.0002&quot;&gt;Pad++: A Zoomable Graphical Sketchpad For Exploring Alternate Interface Physics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;Journal of Visual Languages &amp;amp; Computing&lt;/em&gt; 7, no. 1 (1996): 3–32&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Interactive user interfaces, multiscale interfaces, zoomable interfaces, authoring, information navigation&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Albeit an old paper, it explores the development of new kinds of interactions within software which are quite different from other softwares of the time, and also of the new kinds of HCI.&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;New kinds of approaches, a more human centered approach toward software. The key here is to look at a planet-centered approach toward design.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Raman, Aravindh, Sagar Joglekar, Emiliano De Cristofaro, Nishanth Sastry, and Gareth Tyson&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1145/3355369.3355572&quot;&gt;Challenges in the Decentralised Web&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;Proceedings of the Internet Measurement Conference&lt;/em&gt;, 2019&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Networks, information systems, world wide web, social networks, network measurement&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Explores the Decentralised Web through platforms such as PeerTube, HubZilla, with a focus on Mastodon.&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Important to the sudy of un-centralised edge computational systems&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Conor Linehan, Ben J. Kirman, Stuart Reeves, Mark A. Blythe, Theresa Jean Tanenbaum, Audrey Desjardins, and Ron Wakkary&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1145/2559206.2560472&quot;&gt;Alternate endings: using fiction to explore design futures&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;CHI ‘14 Extended Abstracts on Human Factors in Computing Systems&lt;/em&gt;. Association for Computing Machinery, 2014&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Human-centered computing, design fiction, speculative design&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Paper explores “fictional narratives to envision long-term consequences of contemporary HCI projects”, which is good approach in trying to understand the consequences of the things we create&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Speculative design is always important to the process.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Sanchez-Iborra, Ramon, and Antonio F. Skarmeta&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1109/mcas.2020.3005467&quot;&gt;TinyML-Enabled Frugal Smart Objects: Challenges and Opportunities&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;IEEE Circuits and Systems Magazine&lt;/em&gt; 20, no. 3 (August 13, 2020): 4–18&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Task analysis,  Memory management,  Circuits and systems,  Data security,  Microcontrollers,  Energy efficiency,  Data privacy,  Ecosystems,  Object recognition,  Machine learning&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Explores the use of the TinyML paradigm, which are small microcomputers running ML. A survey of the existing ecosystem is in the paper. It also proposes a framework of a Radio Access Network architecture for smart frugal objects.&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Great introduction to the world of TinyML.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;David, Robert, Jared Duke, Advait Jain, Vijay Janapa Reddi, Nat Jeffries, Jian Li, Nick Kreeger, et al&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2010.08678&quot;&gt;TensorFlow Lite Micro: Embedded Machine Learning on TinyML Systems&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;arXiv.org. Cornell University, October 20, 2020&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Looks at the finer technicalities of running ML models on smaller edge systems&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Banbury, Colby R., C. Zhou, I. Fedorov, R. Navarro, Urmish Thakker, Dibakar Gope, V. Reddi, Matthew Mattina, and P. N. Whatmough&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.semanticscholar.org/paper/MicroNets%3A-Neural-Network-Architectures-for-TinyML-Banbury-Zhou/fd9e3e0b047a6d2b13b7a301e552bc375c8ebe09&quot;&gt;MicroNets: Neural Network Architectures for Deploying TinyML Applications on Commodity Microcontrollers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;ArXiv&lt;/em&gt;abs/2010.11267 (2020)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Executing machine learning workloads locally on resource constrained microcontrollers (MCUs) promises to drastically expand the application space of IoT. However, so-called TinyML presents severe technical challenges, as deep neural network inference demands a large compute and memory budget. To address this challenge, neural architecture search (NAS) promises to help design accurate ML models that meet the tight MCU memory, latency and energy constraints.&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Lin, J., Wei-Ming Chen, Yujun Lin, J. Cohn, Chuang Gan, and Song Han&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.semanticscholar.org/paper/MCUNet%3A-Tiny-Deep-Learning-on-IoT-Devices-Lin-Chen/ea142242898ccc797af88cc633fb8618b272ee62&quot;&gt;MCUNet: Tiny Deep Learning on IoT Devices&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;ArXiv&lt;/em&gt; abs/2007.10319 (2020)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Combine multiple devices to create a local net: MCUNet, a framework that jointly designs the efficient neural architecture (TinyNAS) and the lightweight inference engine (TinyEngine), enabling ImageNet-scale inference on microcontrollers.&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Liu, Di, Hao Kong, X. Luo, Weichen Liu, and R. Subramaniam&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.semanticscholar.org/paper/Bringing-AI-To-Edge%3A-From-Deep-Learning&apos;s-Liu-Kong/75f9918fe00a5bf83092b989e2ed3b9ca0f10a4e&quot;&gt;Bringing AI To Edge: From Deep Learning’s Perspective&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;ArXiv&lt;/em&gt; abs/2011.14808 (2020)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Overview of the Edge world and future development roadmaps&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Vuppalapati, Chandrasekar, Anitha Ilapakurti, Sharat Kedari, Jaya Vuppalapati, Santosh Kedari, and Raja Vuppalapati&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1109/icict50521.2020.00089&quot;&gt;Democratization of AI, Albeit Constrained IoT Devices &amp;amp; Tiny ML, for Creating a Sustainable Food Future&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;2020 3rd International Conference on Information and Computer Technologies (ICICT)&lt;/em&gt;, March 9, 2020&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;develop a framework to deploy artificial intelligence models in constrained compute environments that enable remote rural areas and small farmers to join the data revolution and start contribution to the digital economy and empowers the world through the data to create a sustainable food for our collective future. This is the direction I need to head in. Tiny computers-context-local control-huge win&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Chen, Jiasi, and Xukan Ran&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.semanticscholar.org/paper/Deep-Learning-With-Edge-Computing%3A-A-Review-Chen-Ran/4f2d4e821dd03ac5df7d5448948bc738aefdd6db&quot;&gt;Deep Learning With Edge Computing: A Review&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;Proceedings of the IEEE&lt;/em&gt; 107 (2019): 1655-1674&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Overview of edge sensors and compute modules&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Zhou, Z., X. Chen, E. Li, Liekang Zeng, K. Luo and Junshan Zhang&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.semanticscholar.org/paper/Edge-Intelligence%3A-Paving-the-Last-Mile-of-With-Zhou-Chen/928cd808aba140ec298508df87c5579811ff2f41&quot;&gt;Edge Intelligence: Paving the Last Mile of Artificial Intelligence With Edge Computing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;Proceedings of the IEEE&lt;/em&gt; 107 (2019): 1738-1762&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;a comprehensive survey of the recent research efforts on Edge Intelligence&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Han, Yiwen, X. Wang, Victor C. M. Leung, D. Niyato, Xueqiang Yan and X. Chen&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.semanticscholar.org/paper/Convergence-of-Edge-Computing-and-Deep-Learning%3A-A-Han-Wang/4cd03cd34e7e94d1b1ee293d5dead8efc24c1a6d&quot;&gt;Convergence of Edge Computing and Deep Learning: A Comprehensive Survey&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;IEEE Communications Surveys &amp;amp; Tutorials&lt;/em&gt; 22 (2020): 869-904&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Survey of Edge Intelligence and Edge computing&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Secondary Research</title>
   <link href="https://burnedsap.github.io/ts1https://burnedsap.github.io/ts1/2021/02/03/secondary-research/"/>
   <updated>2021-02-03T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>https://burnedsap.github.io/ts1/2021/02/03/secondary-research</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Doore, Karen. “Alternate Realities for Computational Thinking.” &lt;em&gt;Proceedings of the ninth annual international ACM conference on International computing education research - ICER ‘13&lt;/em&gt;, August 1, 2013. https://doi.org/10.1145/2493394.2493418.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Alternate Reality Games (ARGs) can be utilized as an educational platform to engage students in a collaborative exploration of the field of computing as a means to increase interest in computing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/ms2/media/8938E2D0-072F-435B-AC6F-11CAEB261EC3.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anand, Abhinav, Veljko Pejovic, Elizabeth M. Belding, and David L. Johnson. “VillageCell.” &lt;em&gt;Proceedings of the Fifth International Conference on Information and Communication Technologies and Development - ICTD ‘12&lt;/em&gt;, March 2012. https://doi.org/10.1145/2160673.2160698.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;VillageCell relies on software defined radios and open-source solutions to provide free local and cheap long-distance communication for remote regions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Matthee, K. W., G. Mweemba, A. V. Pais, G. van Stam, and M. Rijken. “Bringing Internet Connectivity to Rural Zambia Using a Collaborative Approach.” &lt;em&gt;2007 International Conference on Information and Communication Technologies and Development&lt;/em&gt;, 2007. https://doi.org/10.1109/ictd.2007.4937391.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The service operates using satellite terminals (for connection to the Internet) and a wireless local area network. The provision of Internet access has enabled local health institutes to operate more effectively and given local people the opportunity to communicate and explore new ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warschauer, Mark. &lt;em&gt;Technology and Social Inclusion: Rethinking the Digital Divide&lt;/em&gt;. Cambridge, MA: MIT, 2004.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Interesting read-nice direction to head in, if obvious&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bederson, Benjamin B., James D. Hollan, Ken Perlin, Jonathan Meyer, David Bacon, and George Furnas. “Pad++: A Zoomable Graphical Sketchpad For Exploring Alternate Interface Physics.” &lt;em&gt;Journal of Visual Languages &amp;amp; Computing&lt;/em&gt; 7, no. 1 (1996): 3–32. https://doi.org/10.1006/jvlc.1996.0002.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;envision a rich world of dynamic persistent informational entities that operate according to multiple physics specifically designed to provide cognitively facile access and serve as the basis for the design of new computationally-based work materials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/ms2/media/C52EF449-99A6-4CFC-8129-075B82EFDEF9.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Raman, Aravindh, Sagar Joglekar, Emiliano De Cristofaro, Nishanth Sastry, and Gareth Tyson. “Challenges in the Decentralised Web.” &lt;em&gt;Proceedings of the Internet Measurement Conference&lt;/em&gt;, 2019. https://doi.org/10.1145/3355369.3355572.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;enabling the operation of web infrastructure and services without centralised ownership or control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conor Linehan, Ben J. Kirman, Stuart Reeves, Mark A. Blythe, Theresa Jean Tanenbaum, Audrey Desjardins, and Ron Wakkary. “Alternate endings: using fiction to explore design futures.” &lt;em&gt;CHI ‘14 Extended Abstracts on Human Factors in Computing Systems&lt;/em&gt;. Association for Computing Machinery, 2014. https://doi.org/10.1145/2559206.2560472&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;fictional narratives to envision long-term consequences of contemporary HCI projects&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sanchez-Iborra, Ramon, and Antonio F. Skarmeta. “TinyML-Enabled Frugal Smart Objects: Challenges and Opportunities.” &lt;em&gt;IEEE Circuits and Systems Magazine&lt;/em&gt; 20, no. 3 (August 13, 2020): 4–18. https://doi.org/10.1109/mcas.2020.3005467.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The TinyML paradigm proposes to integrate Machine Learning (ML)-based mechanisms within small objects powered by Microcontroller Units (MCUs). This paves the way for the development of novel applications and services that do not need the omnipresent processing support from the cloud, which is power consuming and involves data security and privacy risks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David, Robert, Jared Duke, Advait Jain, Vijay Janapa Reddi, Nat Jeffries, Jian Li, Nick Kreeger, et al. “TensorFlow Lite Micro: Embedded Machine Learning on TinyML Systems.” arXiv.org. Cornell University, October 20, 2020. https://arxiv.org/abs/2010.08678.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Looks at the finer technicalities of running ML models on smaller edge systems&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Banbury, Colby R., C. Zhou, I. Fedorov, R. Navarro, Urmish Thakker, Dibakar Gope, V. Reddi, Matthew Mattina, and P. N. Whatmough. “[PDF] MicroNets: Neural Network Architectures for Deploying TinyML Applications on Commodity Microcontrollers: Semantic Scholar.” undefined. Semantic Scholar, 2020. https://www.semanticscholar.org/paper/MicroNets%3A-Neural-Network-Architectures-for-TinyML-Banbury-Zhou/fd9e3e0b047a6d2b13b7a301e552bc375c8ebe09.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Executing machine learning workloads locally on resource constrained microcontrollers (MCUs) promises to drastically expand the application space of IoT. However, so-called TinyML presents severe technical challenges, as deep neural network inference demands a large compute and memory budget. To address this challenge, neural architecture search (NAS) promises to help design accurate ML models that meet the tight MCU memory, latency and energy constraints.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lin, J., Wei-Ming Chen, Yujun Lin, J. Cohn, Chuang Gan, and Song Han. “[PDF] MCUNet: Tiny Deep Learning on IoT Devices: Semantic Scholar.” undefined. Semantic Scholar, 2020. https://www.semanticscholar.org/paper/MCUNet%3A-Tiny-Deep-Learning-on-IoT-Devices-Lin-Chen/ea142242898ccc797af88cc633fb8618b272ee62.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Combine multiple devices to create a local net: MCUNet, a framework that jointly designs the efficient neural architecture (TinyNAS) and the lightweight inference engine (TinyEngine), enabling ImageNet-scale inference on microcontrollers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Liu, Di, Hao Kong, X. Luo, Weichen Liu, and R. Subramaniam. “[PDF] Bringing AI To Edge: From Deep Learning’s Perspective: Semantic Scholar.” undefined. Semantic Scholar, 2020. https://www.semanticscholar.org/paper/Bringing-AI-To-Edge%3A-From-Deep-Learning’s-Liu-Kong/75f9918fe00a5bf83092b989e2ed3b9ca0f10a4e.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Overview of the Edge world and future development roadmaps&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vuppalapati, Chandrasekar, Anitha Ilapakurti, Sharat Kedari, Jaya Vuppalapati, Santosh Kedari, and Raja Vuppalapati. “Democratization of AI, Albeit Constrained IoT Devices &amp;amp; Tiny ML, for Creating a Sustainable Food Future.” &lt;em&gt;2020 3rd International Conference on Information and Computer Technologies (ICICT)&lt;/em&gt;, March 9, 2020. https://doi.org/10.1109/icict50521.2020.00089.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;develop a framework to deploy artificial intelligence models in constrained compute environments that enable remote rural areas and small farmers to join the data revolution and start contribution to the digital economy and empowers the world through the data to create a sustainable food for our collective future. This is the direction I need to head in. Tiny computers-context-local control-huge win&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chen, Jiasi, and Xukan Ran. “[PDF] Deep Learning With Edge Computing: A Review: Semantic Scholar.” Semantic Scholar, 2019. https://www.semanticscholar.org/paper/Deep-Learning-With-Edge-Computing%3A-A-Review-Chen-Ran/4f2d4e821dd03ac5df7d5448948bc738aefdd6db.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Overview of edge sensors and compute modules&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zhou, Z., X. Chen, E. Li, Liekang Zeng, K. Luo and Junshan Zhang. “Edge Intelligence: Paving the Last Mile of Artificial Intelligence With Edge Computing.” &lt;em&gt;Proceedings of the IEEE&lt;/em&gt; 107 (2019): 1738-1762. https://www.semanticscholar.org/paper/Edge-Intelligence%3A-Paving-the-Last-Mile-of-With-Zhou-Chen/928cd808aba140ec298508df87c5579811ff2f41&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;a comprehensive survey of the recent research efforts on Edge Intelligence&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Han, Yiwen, X. Wang, Victor C. M. Leung, D. Niyato, Xueqiang Yan and X. Chen. “Convergence of Edge Computing and Deep Learning: A Comprehensive Survey.” &lt;em&gt;IEEE Communications Surveys &amp;amp; Tutorials&lt;/em&gt; 22 (2020): 869-904. https://www.semanticscholar.org/paper/Convergence-of-Edge-Computing-and-Deep-Learning%3A-A-Han-Wang/4cd03cd34e7e94d1b1ee293d5dead8efc24c1a6d&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Survey of Edge Intelligence and Edge computing&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/blockquote&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Augmentation</title>
   <link href="https://burnedsap.github.io/ts1https://burnedsap.github.io/ts1/2021/01/26/augmentation/"/>
   <updated>2021-01-26T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>https://burnedsap.github.io/ts1/2021/01/26/augmentation</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;augmentation&quot;&gt;Augmentation&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To augment is to make something greater by adding to it, or increasing it. Although this may be a simple definition, it does ask many questions. The chief of which is, should the augmentation happen at all? Can the augmentation even happen? What are the positives and negatives of the augmentation? Augmentation also implies an existing boundary or limit-what does that look like and why is it so?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are the questions which will define the augmentation, and make sense of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps augmentation can also be defined as a verb-to extend, to access, to break barriers, to embrace, to create, to enrich.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 

</feed>
